好的,大家都能听到我讲话吗?
Okay, can everyone hear me okay?
好的,欢迎回来.
Okay, so welcome back.
我想谈一些事务.
I'm gonna address a couple of items in kind of the administratrivia.
第一周结束后,我们发了一封电子邮件
With the end of the first week,we sent an email,
通知你们第一周的视频已经上传,
noticing you that we have uploaded the videos for the first week,
你们可以在网上找到它们.
so you can now find them online.
视频里有课程的全程录像,
They have all the screen recordings for the things that we were doing,
你们回头可以看看,
so you can go back to them.
如果你们对我们某些讲解的很快的东西感到困惑,
Look if you're were confused about if we did something quick
如果对讲义里的任何东西感到疑惑，可以随时向我们提问,.
and, again, feel free to ask us any questions if anything in the lecture notes is not clear.
我们还发了一份调查问卷,你们可以给我们反馈,
We also kind of sent you a survey so you can give us feedback about
告诉我们哪些地方不清楚,或是需要更详细的解释,或者其他任何问题,
what was not clear, what items you would want a more thorough explanation or any other item,
如果你们发现练习太难或太容易,
if you're finding the exercises too hard, too easy,
请在那个网址里留言,我们会非常感激你们的反馈,
go into that URL and we'll really appreciate getting that feedback,
因为这将使接下来的讲座和未来的开课变得更好.
because that will kind of make the course better
for the remaining lectures and for future iterations of the course.
这些事情说完了,
With that out of the way ...
我们尽量及时上传视频,
Oh, and we're gonna try to upload the videos in a more timely manner.
不会等到周末才上传,
We don't want to kind of wait until the end of the week for that.
所以请持续关注.
So keep tuned for that.
这些都说完了,现在我要开始这次讲座了,
That out of the way, now I'm gonna...
这次的讲座是关于命令行环境的,
This lecture's called command-line environment
我们会讲一些不同的话题.
and we're going to cover a few different topics.
我在这里写一下,你们可以方便参考,
So the main topics we're gonna cover, so you can keep track,
可能在这里更好.
it's probably better here, keep track of what I'm talking.
第一个是作业控制,
The first is gonna be job control.
第二个是终端复用器.
The second one is gonna be terminal multiplexers.
然后我会解释什么是dotfiles以及如何配置你的 shell.
Then I'm gonna explain what dotfiles are and how to configure your shell.
最后,如何高效地使用服务器.
And lastly, how to efficiently work with remote machines.
所以如果有什么不清楚的地方,请记住这个结构.
So if things are not fully clear, kind of keep the structure.
它们在一定程度上有交叉,涉及如何使用你的终端,
They all kind of interact in some way, of how you use your terminal,
但它们依然是一些相对独立的话题.
but they are somewhat separate topics, so keep that in mind.
那么我们就来看一下作业控制.
So let's go with job control.
到目前为止,我们使用shell的方式一直很单一,
So far we have been using the shell in a very, kind of mono-command way.
比如,你写一个命令,然后命令被执行,
Like, you execute a command and then the command executes,
然后你得到一些输出,这就是你目前经常做的.
then you get some output, and that's all about what you can do.
如果你想同时运行几个东西,或者如果你想停止一个程序的执行,那就不清楚该怎么做了.
And if you want to run several things, it's not clear how you will do it.
Or if you want to stop the execution of a program,
it's again,
那又该怎么做呢?
like how do I know how to stop a program?
我们可以用一个叫做 "sleep" 的命令来演示这一点.
Let's showcase this with a command called "sleep".
"sleep" 是一个带有参数的命令,
"sleep" is a command that takes an argument,
这个参数是一个整数,执行这个命令后会睡眠.
and that argument is going to be an integer number, and it will sleep.
它会在后台睡眠这么多秒.
It will just kind of be there, on the background, for that many seconds.
如果我们执行类似于 `sleep 20` 的命令,该进程将会休眠 20 秒.
So if we do something like "sleep 20", this process is gonna be sleeping for 20 seconds.
但我们不想等待 20 秒钟才能完成命令.
But we don't want to wait 20 seconds for the command to complete.
因此,我们可以输入 "Ctrl+C".
So what we can do is type "Ctrl+C".
通过输入 "Ctrl+C",我们可以看到,在这里,终端这样("^C")通知我们(进程已经停止),
By typing "Ctrl+C" We can see that, here, the terminal kind of let us know in this,
这是我们在上一节关于vim的讲座中介绍过的一部分,
be one of the syntaxes that we covered in the editors last vim lecture,
我们输入了 "Ctrl+C",它停止了进程的执行.
that we typed "Ctrl+C" and it stopped the execution of the process.
实际上,这里正在使用一种名为信号的 UNIX 通信机制.
What is actually going on here is that this is using a UNIX communication mechanism called signals.
当我们键入 "Ctrl+C" 时,
When we type "Ctrl+C", what the terminal did for us, or the shell did for us,
终端为我们发送了一个名为 "SIGINT" 的信号,该信号表示信号中断,
is send a signal called "SIGINT", that stands for SIGnal INTerrupt,
告诉程序停止自己.
that tells the program to stop itself.
还有许多这样的信号.
And there are many, many, many signals of this kind.
如果你输入 `man signal`,然后向下滚动,你就会看到信号的列表.
If you do "man signal", and just go down a little bit, here you have a list of them.
它们都有数字标识符,
They all have like number identifiers,
名称和一些描述.
they have kind of a short name and you can find a description.
例如,我刚刚描述的信号在这里,编号为 2,是 "SIGINT".
So for example, the one I have just described is here, number 2, "SIGINT".
这是终端在想要中断程序执行时发送给程序的信号.
This is the signal that a terminal will send to a program when it wants to interrupt its execution.
还有一些信号需要熟悉,例如 "SIGQUIT",
A few more to be kind of familiar with is "SIGQUIT",
emm..
this is... again
如果你在终端想要退出程序执行.
if you work from a terminal and you want to quit the execution of a program,
对于大多数程序,它们将执行相同的操作,
which for most programs it will do the same thing.
但现在我们将展示一个不同的程序,
But we're gonna showcase now a program which will be different,
这是将发送的信号.
and this is the signal that will be sent.
有时候可能会有些混淆.
It can be confusing sometimes.
我们来看看这些信号,
Kind of looking at these signals, for example,
例如,"SIGTERM" 在大多数情况下等同于 "SIGINT" 和 "SIGQUIT",
the "SIGTERM" is for most cases equivalent to "SIGINT" and "SIGQUIT"
但是它并不通过终端发送.
but it's just when it's not sent through a terminal.
我们将要介绍的其他一些信号包括 "SIGHUP",
A few more that we're gonna cover is "SIGHUP",
它表示终端出现挂起(hang-up).
it's when there's like a hang-up in the terminal.
例如,当你在终端中运行程序时,
So for example, when you are in your terminal,
如果你关闭终端,但终端中仍在运行一些程序,
if you close your terminal and there are still things running in the terminal,
那么程序将发送该信号告诉所有进程应该关闭,
that's the signal that the program is gonna send to all the processes to tell that they should close,
就像命令行通信中出现了故障,它们现在应该关闭.
like there was a hang-up in the command line communication and they should close now.
信号可以做更多的事情,而不仅仅是要求它们停止,中断程序.
Signals can do more things than just like stopping, like interrupting programs and like asking them to finish.
你可以使用 "SIGSTOP" 暂停程序的执行,
You can for example use the "SIGSTOP" to pause the execution of the program,
然后使用 "SIGCONT" 命令,
and then you can use the "SIGCONT" command for continuing,
使其在稍后的时间点继续执行程序.
to continue the execution of the program at a point later in time.
由于所有这些可能有些抽象,让我们看一些例子.
Since all of this might be slightly too abstract, let's see a few examples.
首先,让我们展示一个 python 程序.
First, let's showcase a python program.
我将非常快速地浏览一遍程序.
I'm going to very quickly go through the program.
这是一个python程序,像大多数python程序一样,
This is a python program, and like most python programs,
它正在导入这个"signal"库并在此处定义这个"handler"函数.
is importing this signal library and is defining this handler here.
这个"handler"是在输出，
And this handler is writing,
"哦,我收到了一个'SIGINT',但我不会停在这里".
"Oh, I got a 'SIGINT', but I'm not gonna stop here".
之后,我们告诉python,当它收到"SIGINT"时,我们希望这个程序停止.
And after that, we kind of tell python that we want this program, when it gets a "SIGINT", to stop.
程序的其余部分是一个非常简单的程序,
The rest of the program is a very silly program
只会打印数字.
that is just gonna be printing numbers.
让我们运行看看.
So let's see this in action.
我们运行`python sigint.py`.
We do "python sigint.py".
它正在计数.
And it's counting.
我们尝试使用"Ctrl+C"来停止它,这会发送"SIGINT",
We try doing "Ctrl+C", this sends a "SIGINT",
但程序实际上并没有停止.
but the program didn't actually stop.
这是因为这个程序不想退出,它可以处理"SIGINT",
This is because we have a way in the program of dealing with this exception, and we didn't want to kind of exit.
如果我们按"Ctrl+\"来发送"SIGQUIT",
If we send a "SIGQUIT", which is done through "Ctrl+\", here,
我们可以看到,由于程序没有处理"SIGQUIT"的方法,
we can see that since the program doesn't have a way of dealing with "SIGQUIT",
它会执行默认操作,即终止程序.
it does the default operation, which is kind of terminate the program.
这有啥用呢?例如,如果有人"Ctrl+C"了你的程序,
And you could use this, for example, if someone "Ctrl+C" your program,
你的程序应该执行某些操作,
and your program is supposed to do something,
例如保存程序的中间状态到文件中,
like you maybe want to save the intermediate state of your program to a file,
以便以后恢复.
so you can recover it for later.
这就是你编写此类处理程序的方法.
This is how you could write a handler like this.
你能再重复一遍问题吗?
Can you repeat the question?
我输入了"Ctrl+C"尝试停止它,但它没有停止,
So what I typed is, I type "Ctrl+C" to try to stop it but it didn't,
因为"SIGINT"被程序捕获了.
because "SIGINT" is captured by the program.
然后我输入了"Ctrl+\",这会发送一个不同的信号"SIGQUIT",
Then I type "Ctrl+\", which sends a "SIGQUIT", which is like a different signal,
而这个信号没有被程序捕获.
and this signal is not captured by the program.
值得一提的是,有一些信号是软件无法捕获的.
It's also worth mentioning that there is a couple of signals that cannot be captured by software.
例如,有一些信号像"SIGKILL"是不能被捕获的.
There is a couple of signals like "SIGKILL" that cannot be captured.
如果这样做,它将终止进程的执行,无论如何.
Like that, it will terminate the execution of the process, no matter what.
这有时可能是有害的.
And it can be sometimes harmful.
你应该不想默认调用它.
You do not want to be using it by default,
因为这可能会留下孤儿进程.
because this can leave for example an orphan child, orphaned children processes.
例如,如果一个进程有其他子进程,它会启动,
Like if a process has other small children processes that it started,
而你"SIGKILL"它,所有子进程都会继续在那里运行,
and you "SIGKILL" it, all of those will keep running in there,
但它们没有了父进程,就很可能会遇到非常奇怪的行为.
but they won't have a parent, and you can might have a really weird behavior going on.
如果我们注销(退出当前用户账户),程序会收到什么信号?
What signal is given to the program if we log off?
如果你注销?
If you log off?
那将是...
That would be...
例如,如果你在ssh连接中关闭连接,那就是挂起信号"SIGHUP",
so for example, if you're in an ssh connection and you close the connection, that is the hang-up signal,"SIGHUP",
我举个例子.
which I'm gonna cover in an example.
这就是会被发送的信号.
So this is what would be sent up.
你可以编写一个包装器(比如异常处理),忽略该信号,
And you could write for example, if you want the process to keep working even if you close that,
以使该进程在关闭时继续工作.
you can write a wrapper around that to ignore that signal.
让我们展示一下"SIGSTOP"和"SIGCONT"能做什么.
Let's display what we could do with the stop and continue.
例如,我们可以启动一个耗时很长的进程.
So, for example, we can start a really long process.
比如我们睡眠一千秒,这将花费很长时间.
Let's sleep a thousand, we're gonna take forever.
我们可以按"Ctrl+C",不对,"Ctrl+Z",
We can "Ctrl+C", "Ctrl+Z", sorry,
如果我们这样做,我们可以看到终端显示"it's suspended".
and if we do "Ctrl+Z" we can see that the terminal is saying "it's suspended".
这实际上意味着该进程被发送了一个"SIGSTOP"信号,
What this actually meant is that this process was sent a "SIGSTOP" signal
现在仍然在那里,你可以继续执行它,
and now is still there, you could continue its execution,
但现在它完全停止运行了,不过依然在后台,
but right now it's completely stopped and in the background
我们可以启动一个不同的程序.
and we can launch a different program.
当我们尝试运行这个程序时,请注意我在末尾加了一个"&".
When we try to run this program, please notice that I have included an "&" at the end.
这告诉bash我希望该程序在后台运行.
This tells bash that I want this program to start running in the background.
这个程序依然是在运行当中,只不过是在后台运行的.
This is kind of related to all these concepts of running programs in the shell, but backgrounded.
程序将开始运行,但不会在提示符旁边显示出来.
And what is gonna happen is the program is gonna start but it's not gonna take over my prompt.
如果我只是运行此命令而没有这个"&"符号,我将无法继续执行任何操作.
If I just ran this command without this, I could not do anything.
在命令完成或我手动终结它之前,我将无法继续使用提示符.
I would have no access to the prompt until the command either finished or I ended it abruptly.
但如果我这样做,它会说"有一个新的进程是这个".
But if I do this, it's saying "oh,like there's a new process which is this".
这是进程的标识号,我们现在可以忽略它.
This is the process identifying number, we can ignore this for now.
如果我键入`jobs`命令,我会得到输出,表示我有一个已暂停的作业,即`sleep 1000`.
And if I type the command "jobs", I get the output that I have a suspended job that is the "sleep 1000" job.
然后我有另一个正在运行的作业,即`nohup sleep 2000`.
And then I have another running job, which is this "NOHUP sleep 2000".
假设我想继续第一个作业.
Say I want to continue the first job.
第一个作业已暂停,不再执行.
The first job is suspended, it's not executing anymore.
我可以通过`bg %1`命令继续执行.
I can continue that doing "bg %1"
"%"是指我想引用这个特定的进程.
That "%" is referring to the fact that I want to refer to this specific process.
现在,如果我这样做并查看作业,现在这个作业再次在运行.
And now, if I do that and I look at the jobs, now this job is running again.
现在两个都在运行.
Now both of them are running.
如果我想停止所有这些,我可以使用"kill"命令.
If I wanted to stop these all, I can use the "kill" command.
"kill"命令用于杀死作业,即停止它们,
The kill command (blabla....) is kind of for killing jobs, which is just like stopping them, intuitively,
这非常有用.
but actually it's really useful.
"kill"命令允许你发送任何类型的Unix信号.
Like the kill command just allows you to send any sort of Unix signal.
例如,在这里,我们不完全杀死它,而是发送一个停止信号.
So here for example, instead of killing it completely, we just send a stop signal.
我将发送一个停止信号,这将再次暂停该进程.
Here I'm gonna send a stop signal, which is gonna pause the process again.
我仍然必须打上标识符,
And I still have to include the identifier,
因为没有标识符,shell将不知道是停止哪一个.
because without the identifier the shell wouldn't know whether to stop the first one or the second one.
现在它说已被暂停,因为有一个信号被发送.
Now that's said this has been suspended, because there was a signal sent.
如果我再次键入`jobs`命令,我们可以看到第二个正在运行,而第一个已被停止.
If I do "jobs", again, we can see that the second one is running and the first one has been stopped.
回到之前的一个问题,如果你关闭终端窗口,会发生什么?
Going back to one of the questions, what happens when you close the shell, for example,
为什么有时候人们会建议
and why sometimes people will say that
在远程会话中运行作业之前使用 "nohup" 命令?
you should use this "nohup" command before your run jobs in a remote session.
这是因为如果我们尝试向第一个作业发送挂起命令,
This is because if we try to send a hang up command to the first job
类似于其他信号,第一个作业将会被挂起,
it's gonna, in a similar fashion as the other signals,
这将终止该作业.
it's gonna hang it up and that's gonna terminate the job.
第一个作业不再存在,而第二个作业仍在运行.
And the first job isn't there anymore whereas we have still the second job running.
然而,如果我们尝试向第二个作业发送信号,
However, if we try to send the signal to the second job what will happen
如果我们现在关闭终端窗口,它仍将继续运行.
if we close our terminal right now is it's still running.
就像 "nohup" 一样,
Like "nohup", what it's doing is kind of encapsulating
它将所执行的命令封装起来,
whatever command you're executing and ignoring wherever you get a hang up signal,
忽略任何挂起信号,并使其继续运行.
and just ignoring that so it can keep running.
如果我们向第二个作业发送"kill"信号,
And if we send the "kill" signal to the second job,
那么它将无法被忽略,这将杀死该作业,无论如何.
that one can't be ignored and that will kill the job, no matter what.
我们就没有任何作业在运行了.
And we don't have any jobs anymore.
作业控制部分就讲完了.
That kind of completes the section on job control.
到目前为止有没有什么问题?有没有什么没有讲清楚的地方?
Any questions so far? Anything that wasn't kind of fully clear?
"bg"是干啥的?
What does "bg" do?
"bg"有两个命令.
So "bg"...There are like two commands.
当你的作业被后台运行并停止时,
Whenever you have a command that has been backgrounded and it is stopped
你可以使用 "bg" ("background"的缩写) 命令来继续在后台运行该进程.
you can use "bg" short for "background" to continue that process running on the background.
这相当于向其发送一个继续信号,使其继续运行.
That's equivalent of just kind of sending it a continue signal, so it keeps running.
然后还有另一个命令叫做 "fg",
And then there's another one which is called "fg",
"fg"用在你想将其恢复到前台并重新连接标准输出.
if you want to kind of recover it to the foreground and you want to reattach your standard output.
好的,作业控制是很有用的,同时我认为了解这些标记同样有用
Okay, good. Jobs are useful and in general, I think knowing about signals can be really beneficial
尤其是在处理一些Unix系统的问题
when dealing with some part of Unix
但是通常情况下
but most of the time what you actually want to do is
当你想要编辑器放在一个窗口里,程序在另一个窗口跑,
something along the lines of having your editor in one side and then the program in another,
并且可能要监视标签中的资源消耗时,
and maybe monitoring what the resource consumption is in our tab.
解决的办法你们应该也看到过很多次了,
We could achieve this using probably what you have seen a lot of the time,
就是打开更多的窗口.
which is just opening more windows.
我们可以一直打开终端窗口.
We can keep opening terminal windows.
但事实是,这种情况有更方便的解决方案,
But the fact is there are kind of more convenient solutions to this
就是使用终端复用器.
and this is what a terminal multiplexer does.
像tmux这样的终端复用器可以让你创建不同的工作空间,
A terminal multiplexer like tmux will let you create different workspaces
让你可以快速地重新组织环境,
that you can work in, and quickly kind of,
而且它有很多功能.
this has a huge variety of functionality,
它可以让你重新设置环境并且会给你不同的会话.
It will let you kind of rearrange the environment  and it will let you have different sessions.
还有一个更古老的命令,叫做"screen",
There's another more older command, which is called "screen",
它可能字面上更容易理解.
that might be more readily available.
我认为这个概念可以推广到两个方面.
But I think the concept kind of extrapolates to both.
我们推荐学习 tmux,
We recommend tmux, that you go and learn it.
实际上我们有相应的练习.
And in fact, we have exercises on it.
现在我将展示一个不同的场景.
I'm gonna showcase a different scenario right now.
当我谈及...
So whenever I talked...
哦,让我做个简短的笔记.
Oh, let me make a quick note.
tmux 有三个核心概念,我会详细讲解.
There are kind of three core concepts in tmux, that I'm gonna go through
主要思想是有所谓的"会话(session)",
and the main idea is that there are what is called "sessions".
会话包含"窗口(window)",而窗口包含"面板(pane)".
Sessions have "windows" and windows have "panes".
记住这个层次结构非常必要.
It's gonna be kind of useful to keep this hierarchy in mind.
你可以将"窗口(window)"基本上等同于其他编辑器和浏览器中的"标签(tabs)".
You can pretty much equate "windows" to what "tabs" are in other editors and others,like for example your web browser.
我将主要介绍你在不同层次上能做什么.
I'm gonna go through the features, mainly what you can do at the different levels.
首先,当我们运行 tmux 时,它会启动一个会话.
So first, when we do tmux, that starts a session.
在这里,现在似乎什么都没有改变,
And here right now it seems like nothing changed
但现在我们在可以理解为另一个 shell 中.
but what's happening right now is we're within a shell that is different from the one we started before.
因此,在我们原本的 shell 中,
So in our shell we started a process,
我们启动了一个进程,即 tmux,然后 tmux 启动了一个不同的进程,即我们当前所在的 shell.
that is tmux and that tmux started a different process, which is the shell we're currently in.
这个很好的一点是,这个 tmux 进程与原始 shell 进程是分开的.
And the nice thing about this is that that tmux process is separate from the original shell process.
在这里,我们可以做一些事情.
So here, we can do things.
例如,我们可以执行`ls -la`,查看里面发生了什么.
We can do "ls -la", for example, to tell us what is going on in here.
然后我们可以开始运行我们的程序,它将在其中运行,
And then we can start running our program, and it will start running in there
我们可以使用"Ctrl+A d"来分离会话.
and we can do "Ctrl+A d", for example, to detach to detach from the session.
如果我们使用"tmux a",那么我们会重新连接到会话.
And if we do "tmux a" that's gonna reattach us to the session.
我们暂且离开那个python计数程序,
So the process, we abandon the process kind of counting numbers.
那是个很简单的python计数程序,我们就让它在那儿跑着,
This really silly python program that was just counting numbers, we like left it running there.
并且如果我们 tmux...
And if we tmux...
嘿,进程仍然在那里运行.
Hey, the process is still running there.
我们可以关闭这个终端并打开一个新的终端,
And we could close this entire terminal and open a new one
我们仍然可以重新连接,因为这个 tmux 会话仍在运行.
and we could still reattach because this tmux session is still running.
再次说明,
Again, we can...
在更深入之前...
Before I go any further.
Pretty much...
与 Vim 不同,它没有模式的概念,
Tmux is unlike Vim, where you have this notion of modes,
而是采用了更类似于 Emacs 的方式,
tmux will work in a more emacsy way, which is every command, pretty much every command in tmux,
你可以emmm
you could enter it through the...
几乎每个 tmux 命令都可以通过其命令行输入.
it has a command line, that we could use.
但我建议你熟悉键位绑定.
But I recommend you to get familiar with the key bindings.
一开始可能有点难以理解,但一旦你熟悉了它们...
It can be somehow non intuitive at first, but once you get used to them...
现在":exit",嗯,"Ctrl+C"
":exit" right now, "Ctrl+C",yeah
当你熟悉了它们之后,你会比使用命令更快地使用键位绑定.
When you get familiar with them, you will be much faster just using the key bindings than using the commands.
关于键位绑定的一个注意点:
One note about the key bindings:
所有的键位绑定都有一个形式,需要你输入一个前缀,然后再按一些其他键.
all the key bindings have a form that is like you type a prefix and then some key.
例如,要分离,我们要按下"Ctrl+A",然后再按"D".
So for example, to detach we do "Ctrl+A" and then "D".
这意味着你首先按下"Ctrl+A",然后松开它,再按"D"来分离.
This means you press "Ctrl+A" first, you release that, and then press "D" to detach.
在默认的tmux中,前缀是"Ctrl+B",
On default tmux, the prefix is "Ctrl+B",
但你会发现大多数人将其重新映射为"Ctrl+A",
but you will find that most people will have this remapped to "Ctrl+A"
因为在键盘上更加人性化.
because it's a much more ergonomic type on the keyboard.
你可以在练习中了解更多关于如何进行这些操作的信息,
You can find more about how to do these things in one of the exercises,
我们会链接到基础知识和如何利用tmux进行效率提升.
where we link you to the basics and how to do some kind of quality of life modifications to tmux.
回到会话的概念,
Going back to the concept of sessions,
我们可以通过像`tmux new`这样的命令创建一个新的会话,我们可以给会话命名.
we can create a new session just doing something like "tmux new" and we can give sessions names.
所以我们可以像`tmux new -t foobar`这样做,这是一个完全不同的会话,我们已经开始了.
So we can do like "tmux new -t foobar" and this is a completely different session, that we have started.
我们可以在这里工作,也可以从中分离出来.
We can work here, we can detach from it.
`tmux ls`会告诉我们我们有两个不同的会话:
"tmux ls" will tell us that we have two different sessions:
第一个是命名为"0",因为我没有给它命名,
the first one is named "0", because I didn't give it a name,
第二个被称为"foobar".
and the second one is called "foobar".
我可以连接到"foobar"会话,也可以结束它.
I can attach the "foobar" session and I can end it.
这非常好,因为有了这个,你可以在完全不同的项目中工作.
And it's really nice because having this you can kind of work in completely different projects.
例如,有两个不同的tmux会话和不同的编辑器会话,不同的进程正在运行......
For example, having two different tmux sessions and different editor sessions, different processes running...
当你在一个会话中时,我们从窗口的概念开始讲起.
When you are within a session, we start with the concept of windows.
这里我们有一个单独的窗口,但是我们可以使用"Ctrl+A c"("c"表示"create")来创建一个新窗口.
Here we have a single window, but we can use "Ctrl+A c" (for "create") to open a new window.
这里没有执行任何操作.
And here nothing is executing.
它的作用是,tmux为我们打开了一个新的shell,我们可以在这里运行这些程序.
What it's doing is, tmux has opened a new shell for us and we can start running another one of these programs here.
为了快速跳转标签,我们可以按"Ctrl+A p",
And to quickly jump between the tabs, we can do "Ctrl+A p",
"p"(表示"previous")来切换到上一个窗口.
"p" for "previous", and that will go up to the previous window.
"Ctrl+A n"("n"表示"next")来到下一个窗口.
"Ctrl+A n", to go to the next window.
你也可以使用数字.
You can also use the numbers.
所以如果我们打开了很多这些标签,
So if we start opening a lot of these tabs,
我们可以使用"Ctrl+A 1"来特定地跳转到编号为"1"的窗口.
we could use "Ctrl+A 1", to specifically jump to the to the window that is number "1".
最后,当然你也可以重新命名它们.
And, lastly, it's also pretty useful to know sometimes that you can rename them.
例如,这里我正在执行这个python进程,
For example here I'm executing this python process,
但是这个窗口不能见名知意,我想......
but that might not be really informative and I want...
我可能想要有像"execution"之类的名字,
I maybe want to have something like "execution" or something like that
那我们就可以重新命名该窗口的名称,以便有个良好的窗口管理.
and that will rename the name of that window so you can have this really neatly organized.
这样做并不能满足你想要在终端中同时显示两个栏目的需求.
This still doesn't solve the need when you want to have two things at the same time in your terminal,like in the same display.
这就是面板(pane)存在的原因.
This is what panes are for.
现在,我们有一个只有一个面板的窗口
Right now, here we have a window with a single pane
到目前为止,我们打开的所有窗口都只有一个面板.
all the windows that we have opened so far have a single pane.
但是如果我们按下`Ctrl+A "`,这将把当前显示屏分成两个不同的面板.
But if we do 'Ctrl+A "', this will split the current display into two different panes.
你看,我们打开的下面的窗口是一个新的shell,
So, you see, the one we open below is a different shell from the one we have above,
我们可以在这里运行任何进程.
and we can run any process that we want here.
我们可以继续分裂,如果我们按下`Ctrl+A %`,那么就会垂直分裂.
We can keep splitting this, if we do "Ctrl+A %" that will split vertically.
你可以使用许多不同的命令来重新排列这些选项卡.
And you can kind of rearrange these tabs using a lot of different commands.
其中一个我发现非常有用的命令是,当你需要重新排列它们.
One that I find very useful, when you are starting and it's kind of frustrating, rearranging them.
要移动这些面板,
Before I explain that, to move through these panes,
这是你想一直做的事情,
which is something you want to be doing all the time
你只需按下"Ctrl+A"和箭头键,
You just do "Ctrl+A" and the arrow keys,
这样就可以快速浏览不同的窗口
and that will let you quickly navigate through the different windows,
并再次执行操作...
and execute again...
比如我正在做很多`ls -la`,我可以做`htop`,
Like I'm doing a lot of "ls -la", I can do "htop",
我们将在调试和分析讲座中解释这个.
that we'll explain in the debugging and profiling lecture.
我们可以浏览它们,
And we can just navigate through them,
重新组织它们一样,还有一堆其他的命令,
again like to rearrange there's another slew of commands,
你可以在练习中学习,`Ctrl+A ` 是个很有用的命令,
you will go through some in the exercises, "Ctrl+A " is pretty neat,
因为它会将当前的选项卡等距分布,
because it will kind of equispace the current ones
让你可以进行不同的布局.
and let you through different layouts.
有些布局里的窗口太小了.
Some of them are too small for my current terminal config.
我现在已经讲了tmux的大部分内容.
but that covers, I think, most of it.
哦,还有,例如,
Oh, there's also, here, for example,
这个已经启动了的vim程序界面,对于当前的tmux面板来说太小了.
this vim execution that we have started, is too small for what the current tmux pane is.
因此,相对于拥有多个终端窗口,
So one of the things that really is much more convenient to do in tmux,
一个非常方便的事情就是可以在tmux中放大它,
in contrast to having multiple terminal windows,
你可以通过按下"Ctrl+A z"来要求"扩张".
is that you can zoom into this, you can ask by doing "Ctrl+A z", for "zoom".
它会扩展面板占据所有的空间,
It will expand the pane to take over all the space,
然后再按下"Ctrl+A z"即可返回.
and then "Ctrl+A z" again, will go back to it.
对于终端多路复用器或tmux有什么问题吗?
Any questions for terminal multiplexers, or like, tmux concretely?
它们是在运行所有相同的东西吗?
Is it running all the same thing?
在不同的窗口中运行是否有任何执行差异?
Like, is there any difference in execution between running it in different windows or like different (blabla...)?
tmux分割开的shell是否完全相同?我的问题说清楚了吗?
Is it really just doing it all the same, so that you can see it?
是的,它不会与在计算机中打开两个终端窗口有任何区别.
Yeah, it wouldn't be any different from having two terminal windows open in your computer.
就像他们两个一起被执行一样
Like both of them are gonna be running.
当然,当它到达CPU时,这将再次进行多路复用.
Of course, when it gets to the CPU, this is gonna be multiplexed again.
就像有一个时间共享机制,但没有任何区别.
Like there's like a timesharing mechanism going there but there's no difference.
tmux通过为你提供这个
like tmux is just making this much more convenient to use
可以快速操作的可视化布局,使用会变得更加方便.
by giving you kind of this visual layout that you can quickly manipulate through.
其中有一项优势会在我们等会讲解服务器时体现,
And one of the main advantages will come when we reach the remote machines
因为你可以留下其中之一,
because you can leave one of these,
我们可以从其中一个tmux系统中分离出来,
we can detach from one of these tmux systems,
关闭连接,即使我们关闭连接
close the connection and even if we close the connection
并且终端将发送挂起信号,
and the terminal is gonna send a hang-up signal,
但这也不会关闭所有已启动的tmux.
that's not gonna close all the tmuxes that have been started.
还有其他问题吗?
Any other questions?
让我禁用按键记录器.
Let me disable the key-caster.
现在我们要开始讲解dotfiles,
So now we're gonna move into the topic of dotfiles and,
以及一般如何配置你的shell以执行你想要执行的任务,
in general, how to kind of configure your shell to do the things you want to do
主要是如何更快地更方便地执行它们.
and mainly how to do them quicker and in a more convenient way.
首先要讲一下别名,别名就是一个很方便的东西.
I'm gonna motivate this using aliases first.
所谓别名,就是现在,某件事儿你可能需要做很多次,
So what an alias is, is that by now, you might be starting to do something like a lot of the time,
例如,我想查看一个目录,并将所有内容以列表格式和可读格式显示出来.
I just want to ls a directory and I want to display all the contents into a list format and in a human readable thing.
这很好.
And it's fine.
它不是那么长的命令.
Like it's not that long of a command.
但是,随着你构建越来越长的命令,
But as you start building longer and longer commands,
反复输入它们可能会变得有点麻烦.
it can become kind of bothersome having to retype them again and again.
别名在这种情况下就可以非常方便.
This is one of the reasons why aliases are useful.
别名可以映射长命令为一个短的字符串,
Alias is a command that will be a built-in in your shell,
然后内置在你的shell当中.
and what it will do is it will remap a short sequence of characters to a longer sequence.
例如,如果我执行`alias ll="ls -lah"`,
So if I do, for example, here `alias ll="ls -lah"`
If I execute this command, this is gonna call the "alias" command with this argument
然后我的shell环境就会知道这个映射的存在.
and this is gonna update the environment in my shell to be aware of this mapping.
因此,如果我现在执行`ll`,他将会执行`ls -lah`,我们不必键入完整的命令.
So if I now do "ll", it's executing that command without me having to type the entire command.
它可以非常方便,有很多很多用途.
It can be really handy for many, many reasons.
需要注意的一件事是,
One thing to note before I go any further is that here,
这里的"alias"与其他命令没有什么特殊之处,
"alias" is not anything special compared to other commands,
它只是接受单个参数.
it's just taking a single argument.
在等号周围不能有空格,因为别名只接受一个参数,
And there is no space around this equals and that's because alias takes a single argument
如果你你在等号周围加空格,它会认为你给了它超过了一个参数,
and if you try doing something like this, that's giving it more than one argument
那是不起作用的,因为那不符合它的格式.
and that's not gonna work because that's not the format it expects.
除此之外,别名还有其他用法,
So other use cases that work for aliases,
例如,对于某些事情来说,使用别名可能更方便,
as I was saying, for some things it might be much more convenient,
比如我的最爱之一就是`git status`.
like one of my favorites is "git status".
它非常长,我不喜欢经常输入那么长的命令,
It's extremely long, and I don't like typing that long of a command every so often,
因为这最终会花费很多时间.
because you end up taking a lot of time.
因此,把`git status`替换为"gs".
So "gs" will replace for doing the "git status"
你还可以使用别名来更正经常打错的命令.比如说"sl=ls".
You can also use them to alias things that you mistype often, so you can do "sl=ls",that will work.
其他有用的映射方式是,
Other useful mappings are,
你可能想将一个命令取别名为带有选项的自身.
you might want to alias a command to itself but with a default flag.
比如我现在要创建一个别名,
So here what is going on is I'm creating an alias
它是移动命令的别名,
which is an alias for the move command,
即"mv",并将其别名为相同的命令,但添加了"-i"标志.
which is mv and I'm aliasing it to the same command but adding the "-i" flag.
如果你查看man页面,
And this "-i" flag, if you go through the man page and look at it,
你会发现"-i"标志代表"interactive".
it stands for "interactive".
这将在我覆盖文件之前提示我.
And what it will do is it will prompt me before I do an overwrite.
一旦我执行了这个命令,我就可以像这样移动"aliases.sh"到"case.sh".
So once I have executed this, I can do something like I want to move "aliases.sh" into "case.sh".
默认情况下,"mv"命令不会询问,如果"case.sh"已经存在,它将被覆盖.
By default "mv" won't ask, and if "case.sh" already exists, it will be over.
那很好,我要覆盖那里的任何东西.
That's fine, I'm going to overwrite whatever that's there.
但现在,"mv"已经被扩展为"mv -i",
But here it's now expanded,"mv" has been expanded into this "mv -i"
执行它会来询问"你确定要覆盖它吗?
and it's using that to ask me "Oh, are you sure you want to overwrite this?"
我可以选择不覆盖,以避免丢失文件.
And I can say no, I don't want to lose that file.
最后,你可以使用`alias mv`命令来查询这个别名的含义.
Lastly, you can use "alias mv" to ask for what this alias stands for.
这样可以快速确定
So it will tell you so you can quickly make sure
你实际执行的命令是什么.
what the command that you are actually executing is.
例如,有一个不方便的部分是,
One inconvenient part about, for example, having aliases is
如果你有别名,那么如何将它们持久化到你当前的环境中呢?
how will you go about persisting them into your current environment?
如果我现在关闭这个终端,所有这些别名都会消失.
Like, if I were to close this terminal now, all these aliases will go away.
你不想一遍又一遍地重新输入这些命令.
And you don't want to be kind of retyping these commands and more generally,
更一般地说,如果你开始配置你的shell,你需要某种方式来存储所有这些配置.
if you start configuring your shell more and more, you want some way of bootstrapping all this configuration.
你会发现大多数shell命令程序都使用一些基于文本的配置文件.
You will find that most shell command programs will use some sort of text based configuration file.
由于历史原因,我们通常称其为"dotfiles",因为它们以"."开头.
And this is what we usually all "dotfiles", because they start with a dot for historical reasons.
所以对于我们的shell,比如bash,我们可以查看".bashrc"文件.
So for bash in our case, which is a shell, we can look at the ".bashrc".
作为演示,这里我一直在使用zsh,
For demonstration purposes, here I have been using zsh,
这是一个不同的shell,我将会配置bash,然后启动bash.
which is a different shell, and I'm gonna be configuring bash, and starting bash.
所以比如我在这里创建一个条目,
So if I create an entry here and I say
我说`sl`映射到`ls`.我已经修改了它,现在我启动bash.
"sl" maps to "ls". And I have modified that, and now I start bash.
bash现在是完全未配置的,但现在如果我输入`sl`...
bash is kind of completely unconfigured, but now if I do "sl"...
芜湖~翻车了.
Hm, that's unexpected.
哦,好的.
Oh, good. Good getting that.
那很重要,
So it matters where you config file is,
你的配置文件要放在你的home目录中.
your config file needs to be in your home folder.
因此,bash的配置文件将位于"~"中,
So your configuration file for bash will live in that "~",
它会扩展到你的home目录,然后是".bashrc".
which will expand to your home directory, and then ".bashrc".
在这里,我们可以创建别名,现在我们开启一个bash会话并运行`sl`.
And here we can create the alias and now we start a bash session and we do "sl".
现在它已经加载了这个别名,在bash程序启动时即加载了所有的配置.
Now it has been loaded, and this is loaded at the beginning when this bash program is started.
现在不仅可以使用别名,还可以有很多其他的配置.
And all this configuration is loaded, and you can not only use aliases, they can have a lot of parts of configuration.
例如,在这里,我有一个相当无用的提示符.
So for example here, I have a prompt which is fairly useless.
它只告诉我使用的shell名称是bash,版本是5.0.
Like it has just given me the name of the shell, which is bash, and the version, which is 5.0.
我不想显示它,而且在你的shell中也有许多像这样没啥用的东西,
I don't want this to be displayed and as with many things in your shell,
这只是一个环境变量.
this is just an environment variable.
"PS1"是提示你输入的字符串(这里原来是"bash-5.0$"),
So the "PS1" is just the prompt string for your prompt
我们实际上可以修改它,使其成为一个"> ".
and we can actually modify this to just be a "> " symbol.
现在已经修改过了,我们已经有了这个.
and now that has been modified, and we have that.
但是,如果我们退出并再次调用bash,这个修改就会丢失.
But if we exit and call bash again, that was lost.
但是,如果我们添加这个条目并说,
However, if we add this entry and say,
我们希望"PS1"是这样的,然后再次调用bash,
oh we want "PS1" to be this and we call bash again,
这个修改就会被保留下来.
this has been persisted.
我们可以继续修改这个配置.
And we can keep modifying this configuration.
所以也许我们想在提示符里显示出我们当前的工作目录,
So maybe we want to include where the working directory that we are in,
这就和其他shell里我们看到的一样了.
and that's telling us the same information that we had in the others.
还有许多许多选项,Shell是高度可配置的,
And there are many, many options, like shells are highly, highly configurable,
不仅是通过这些文件配置Shell,
and it's not only shells that are configured through these files,
还有许多其他程序.
there are many other programs.
就像我们在编辑器讲座中看到的那样,Vim也是通过这种方式进行配置的.
As we saw for example in the editors lecture, Vim is also configured this way.
我们给你这个vimrc文件,并告诉你将它放在"~/.vimrc"下,
We gave you this vimrc file and told you to put it under your "~/.vimrc"
这是相同的概念,但只是针对Vim.
and this is the same concept, but just for Vim.
即在启动时让它加载一系列的指令,
It's just giving it a set of instructions that it should load when it's started,
以便你可以保持所需的配置.
so you can keep a configuration that you want.
甚至许多程序也支持这种方式.
And even (non...) kind of a lot of programs will support this.
例如,我的终端模拟器,这是另一个概念,
For instance, my terminal emulator, which is another concept,
是运行shell的程序,并将其显示在计算机屏幕上.
which is the program that is running the shell, in a way, and displaying this into the screen in my computer.
它也可以通过这种方式进行配置,因此如果我修改它,我可以更改字体的大小.
It can also be configured this way, so if I modify this I can change the size of the font.
例如,现在,我已经为演示目的增加了字体大小,
Like right now, for example, I have increased the font size a lot for demonstration purposes,
但如果我更改这个条目并使其为28,然后写入这个值,
but if I change this entry and make it for example 28 and write this value,
你会发现字体的大小已经改变了,
you see that the size of the font has changed,
因为我编辑了这个配置文件,它指定了我的终端模拟器应该如何工作.
because I edited this text file that specifies how my terminal emulator should work.
还有其他问题关于dotfiles吗?
Any questions so far? With dotfiles.
好的,知道有这么多的配置可能会让人感到有些不知所措,是吗?
Okay, it can be a bit daunting knowing that there is like this endless wall of configurations,
你咋知道哪些内容可以进行配置呢?
and how do you go about learning about what can be configured?
好消息是,我们在讲义中已经为你提供了非常好的资源链接.
The good news is that we have linked you to really good resources in the lecture notes.
很多人喜欢配置这些工具,
But the main idea is that a lot of people really like just configuring these tools
他们把自己的配置文件上传到了GitHub这样的在线仓库中.
and have uploaded their configuration files to GitHub,
another different kind of repositories online.
例如,在GitHub上
So for example, here we are on GitHub,
搜索"dotfiles",你会发现
we search for "dotfiles", and can see that
有成千上万的人在分享他们的配置文件.
there are like thousands of repositories of people sharing their configuration files.
我们的课程导师也链接了我们的dotfiles.
We have also like, the class instructors have linked our dotfiles.
因此,如果你想知道我们配置中的每一行是如何工作的,
So if you really want to know how any part of our setup is working
你可以查看这些文件并尝试弄清楚.
you can go through it and try to figure it out.
也欢迎你们随时向我们询问.
You can also feel free to ask us.
例如,如果我们转到这个仓库,
If we go for example to this repository here
我们会发现有很多文件可以配置.
we can see that there's many, many files that you can configure.
例如,有一个用于bash的文件,前几个用于git,
For example, there is one for bash, the first couple of ones are for git,
这些可能会在版本控制讲座中进行介绍.
that will be probably be covered in the version control lecture tomorrow.
如果我们例如转到bash配置文件,它是一种不同形式的bashrc,
If we go for example to the bash profile, which is a different form of what we saw in the bashrc,
它非常有用,因为你可以通过查看手册页来学习,
it can be really useful because you can learn through just looking at the manual page,
但是手册页通常只是所有不同选项的描述性解释,
but the manual pages is, a lot of the time just kind of like a descriptive explanation of all the different options
我们可以通过看其他人的示例并尝试理解他们为什么这样做
and sometimes it's more helpful going through examples of what people have done and trying to understand why they did it
以及它如何完善他们的工作流程来学习.
and how it's helping their workflow.
我们可以看到这里已经进行了不区分大小写的文件名扩展操作.
We can say here that this person has done case-insensitive globbing.
我们在shell脚本和工具中介绍了globbing(通配符扩展)这种文件名展开技巧.
We covered globbing as this kind of filename expansion trick in the shell scripting and tools.
这里你说"不,我不想区分大小写."
And here you say no, I don't want this to matter, whether using uppercase and lowercase,
只需在shell中设置此选项即就可使shell按照你期望的方式运行.
and just setting this option in the shell for these things to work this way
类似地,还有一些别名.
Similarly, there is for example aliases.
在这里,你可以看到这个人正在做很多别名.
Here you can see a lot of aliases that this person is doing.
例如,"d"代表"cd ~/Document/Dropbox"
For example, "d" for "cd ~/Document/Dropbox"
因为这样更短.
sorry, because that's just much shorter.
"g"代表"git"...
"g" for "git"...
我们来看一下vimrc.
Say we go, for example, with vimrc.
通过查看它并尝试提取有用信息,这些文件实际上信息量很大.
It can be actually very, very informative, going through this and trying to extract useful information.
我们不建议只是将一个巨大的配置文件复制到你的配置文件中,
We do not recommend just kind of getting one huge blob of this and copying this into your config files,
虽然这可能看起来更漂亮,但你可能真的不了解其中的细节.
because maybe things are prettier, but you might not really understand what is going on.
最后,关于dotfiles我想提到的一件事是,
Lastly one thing I want to mention about dotfiles is that
人们将这些文件推送到GitHub中
people not only try to push these files into GitHub
以便其他人阅读,这是其中一个原因.
just so other people can read it, that's one reason.
这样还确保他们可以很快重现他们的配置.
They also make really sure they can reproduce their setup.
为此,他们使用了各种不同的工具.
And to do that they use a slew of different tools.
扯得有点远了
Oops, went a little too far.
例如GNU Stow,
So GNU Stow is, for example, one of them
他们的技巧是,
and the trick that they are doing is
他们将所有的dotfiles都放在一个文件夹中,并通过一个工具瞒天过海,
they are kind of putting all their dotfiles in a folder and they are kind of faking to the system,
这是一种名为符号链接的工具,它会让伪装的文件看起来是真的.
using a tool called symlinks, that they are actually what they're not.
我来快速画一下我所说的意思.
I'm gonna draw really quick what I mean by that.
通常的文件夹结构可能是这样的:你有你的home文件夹,
So a common folder structure might look like you have your home folder
在这个home文件夹中可能会有你的bashrc,
and in this home folder you might have your bashrc,
它包含了你的bash配置,你可能会有你的vimrc,
that contains your bash configuration, you might have your vimrc
如果你能把它们放在git下就太好了.
and it would be really great if you could keep this under version control.
但是问题是,你可能不想在你的home文件夹中放置一个git仓库.
But the thing is, you might not want to have a git repository,
关于git的内容明天会讲到
which will be covered tomorrow, in your home folder.
所以人们通常会创建一个dotfiles仓库,
So what people usually do is they create a dotfiles repository,
然后在这里为他们的bashrc和vimrc创建条目.
and then they have entries here for their bashrc and their vimrc.
这其实就是文件所在的地方,
And this is where actually the files are
他们只是告诉操作系统,
and what they are doing is they're just telling the OS to forward,
无论何时有人想要读取这个文件或者写入这个文件,
whenever anyone wants to read this file or write to this file,
都把这个请求转移到请求另一个文件.
just forward this to this other file.
这是一个叫做符号链接的概念,在这种情况下很有用,
This is a concept called symlinks and it's useful in this scenario,
它通常是UNIX中一个非常有用的工具,
but it in general it's a really useful tool in UNIX
我们在讲座中还没有涉及到,
that we haven't covered so far in the lectures
但是你应该熟悉.
but you might be... that you should be familiar with.
通常情况下,语法是使用"ln -s"指定一个符号链接,
And in general, the syntax will be "ln -s" for specifying a symbolic link
然后把你想要创建的文件的路径
and then you will put the path to the file
和你想要创建的符号链接放在一起.
that you want to create and then the symlink that you want to create.
...
所有这些高级工具,我们在这里列出来的,
And all these kind of fancy tools that we're seeing here listed,
它们都可以用一些技巧实现,
they all amount to doing some sort of this trick,
这样你就可以把所有的dotfiles整齐地放在一个文件夹里,
so that you can have all your dotfiles neat and tidy into a folder,
它们可以使用git来管理,
and then they can be version-controlled,
也可以被符号链接,这样其它程序可以在它们的默认位置找到它们.
and they can be symlinked so the rest of the programs can find them in their default locations.
关于dotfiles有什么问题吗?
Any questions regarding dotfiles?
你需要在你的home文件夹
Do you need to have the dotfiles in your home folder,
和git文件夹中都有dotfiles吗?
and then also dotfiles in the version control folder?
几乎每个程序,例如,
So what you will have is, pretty much every program, for example
bash程序总是会查找"~/.bashrc".
bash will always look for "~/.bashrc".
这就是程序要查找的位置.
That's where the program is going to look for.
当你创建一个符号链接时,你把你的"~/.bashrc"放在一个特殊的UNIX文件中,
What you do when you do a symlink is, you place your "~/.bashrc"
这个文件只是Unix中的一种特殊的文件,
it's just a file that is kind of a special file in UNIX,
它说:"无论何时你想读取这个文件,都要去找那个文件."
that says oh, whenever you want to read this file go to this other file.
这个文件没有内容,
There's no content, like there is no...
比如你的别名不是这个dotfiles的一部分.
your aliases are not part of this dotfile.
这个文件只是一个指针,告诉你应该取哪个地址
That file is just kind of like a pointer, saying now you should go that other way.
通过这样做,你可以把你的其他文件放在那个文件夹中.
And by doing that you can have your other file in that other folder.
如果版本控制没有用处,那么想一想如果你想将它们放到Dropbox文件夹中,
If version controlling is not useful, think about what if you want to have them in your Dropbox folder,
这样它们就可以同步到云端,
so they're synced to the cloud, for example.
还有另一种情况,这时符号链接也非常有用,
That's kind of another use case where like symlinks could be really useful
你不需要将dotfiles文件夹放在主目录中,对吧?
So you don't need the folder dotfiles to be in the home directory, right?
因为你可以使用符号链接,指向其他位置.
Because you can just use the symlink, that points somewhere else.
只要你有一种方式让默认路径解析到你所在的位置就可以了.
As long as you have a way for the default path to resolve wherever you have it, yeah.
最后我想说...
Last thing I want to cover in the lecture...
哦,抱歉,有没有其他关于dotfiles的问题?
Oh, sorry, any other questions about dotfiles?
最后我想在讲座中讨论一下与远程服务器的交互,
Last thing I want to cover in the lecture is working with remote machines,
这是你迟早都要碰到的.
which is a thing that you will run into, sooner or later.
如果你知道一些东西,
And there are a few things that will make your life much easier
它们会让你在与远程服务器交互时更加轻松.
when dealing with remote machines if you know about them.
也许现在因为你在使用Athena集群(MIT提供的一种高性能计算机资源共享平台，Athena用户可以通过网络连接到这个集群上运行科学计算程序.),
Right now maybe because you are using the Athena cluster,
但在你的编程生涯中,
but later on, during your programming career,
有一个非常普遍的概念,就是你有你的本地工作环境,
it's pretty sure that there is a fairly ubiquitous concept of having kind of your local working environment
然后有一些运行代码的生产服务器,你需要得到服务器上的一些信息
and then having some production server that is actually running the code, really good to get for me,
因此熟悉如何与远程服务器进行交互非常重要.
so it is really good to get familiar about how to work in/with remote machines.
处理远程服务器的主要命令是"ssh".
So the main command for working with remote machines is "ssh".It's "ssh".
"ssh"就像一个安全的Shell,它将负责送我们到想要到达的地方
"ssh" is just like a secure shell, it's just gonna take the responsibility for kind of reaching wherever we want
或者告诉它在那个地方去打开一个会话.
or tell it to go and trying to kind of open a session there.
这里的语法是:
So here the syntax is:
"jjgo"是我在远程服务器上使用的用户名,
"jjgo" is the user that I want to use in the remote machine,
这是因为该用户与我本地机器上的用户不同,
and this is because the user is different from the one I have my local machine,
这在很多情况下都是这样,
which will be the case a lot of the time,
然后"@"告诉终端这个符号分离了用户和地址.
then the "@" is telling the terminal that this separates what the user is from what the address is.
这里我使用的是一个IP地址,
And here I'm using an IP address
因为现在要连接的远程的服务器实际上是我的电脑里的一个虚拟机,
because what I'm actually doing is I have a virtual machine in my computer,
that is the one that is remote right now.
我将要通过ssh连接它.
And I'm gonna be ssh'ing into it.
这是我使用的URL,抱歉,
This is the URL that I'm using, sorry,
我使用的IP地址,但是你也可能会看到类似这样的东西:
the IP that I'm using, but you might also see things like
我想以在"foobar.mit.edu"上以"jjgo"的名义使用ssh.
oh I want to ssh as "jjgo" at "foobar.mit.edu"
如果你使用一些具有DNS名称的远程服务器,这可能是更常见的.
That's probably something more common, if you are using some remote server that has a DNS name.
回到常规命令,
So going back to a regular command,
我们尝试ssh,它会要求我们输入密码,这是很正常.
we try to ssh, it asks us for a password, really common thing.
现在我们已经连接成功了.
And now we're there. We have...
我们仍然在我们同一个终端模拟器中,
we're still in our same terminal emulator
但现在ssh会将远程shell正在显示的内容转发到当前的界面
but right now ssh is kind of forwarding the entire virtual display to display
what the remote shell is displaying.
我们可以在这里执行命令并查看远程文件.
And we can execute commands here and we'll see the remote files
关于ssh,
A couple of handy things to know about ssh,
有一些简便的操作在数据整理讲座中简要介绍过,
that were briefly covered in the data wrangling lecture,
它不仅仅适用于连接,
is that ssh is not only good for just opening connections.
还可以让你远程执行命令.
It will also let you just execute commands remotely.
例如,如果我这样做,它会再次询问我的密码.
So for example, if I do that, it's gonna ask me "what is my password?" again.
它会执行这个命令,然后回到我的终端,
And it's executing this command then coming back to my terminal
并通过当标准输出将该命令的结果,
and piping the output of what that command was, in the remote machine,
也就是远程服务器的输出,传输过来.
through the standard output in my current shell.
然后我可以使用这个.
And I could have this in...
我可以将其放入管道中,
I could have this in a pipe, and this will work
并在本地管道中继续工作.
and we'll just drop all this output and then have a local pipe where I can keep working.
到目前为止,老是要输入密码有点不方便.
So far, it has been kind of inconvenient, having to type our password.
有一个很好的技巧可以解决这个问题.
There's one really good trick for this.
它就是我们一个叫"ssh密钥"的东西.
It's we can use something called "ssh keys".
ssh密钥使用公钥加密来创建一对ssh密钥,
ssh keys just use public key encryption to create a pair of ssh keys,
一个公钥和一个私钥,然后你可以将公钥部分给服务器.
a public key and a private key, and then you can give the server the public part of the key.
因此,你复制公钥,每当你尝试进行身份验证时,
So you copy the public key and then whenever you try to authenticate instead of using your password,
它将使用私钥向服务器证明你就是你
it's gonna use the private key to prove to the server
that you are actually who you say you are.
我们可以快速展示如何做到这一点.
We can quickly showcase how you will go about doing this.
现在我没有任何ssh密钥,所以我要创建一对.
Right now I don't have any ssh keys, so I'm gonna create a couple of them.
第一件事,它会问我想让这个密钥存储在哪里.
First thing, it's just gonna ask me where I want this key to live.
显然,它正在执行这个操作.
Unsurprisingly, it's doing this.
这是我的home文件夹,然后它使用这个".ssh"路径,
This is my home folder and then it's using this ".ssh" path,
这是我们之前提到过的dotfiles的概念.
which refers back to the same concept that we covered earlier about having dotfiles.
".ssh"是一个包含许多配置文件的文件夹,用于配置ssh.
Like ".ssh" is a folder that contains a lot of the configuration files for how you want ssh to behave.
因此,它会要求我们输入一个密码.
So it will ask us a passphrase.
这个密码是用来加密密钥的私钥部分的,
The passphrase is to encrypt the private part of the key
因为如果有人得到了你的私钥,
because if someone gets your private key,
如果你的私钥没有受到密码保护,
if you don't have a password protected private key,
如果他们得到了那个私钥,他们就可以在服务器上冒充你.
if they get that key they can use that key to impersonate you in any server.
而如果你添加了密码,他们必须知道密码才能使用私钥.
Whereas if you add a passphrase, they will have to know what the passphrase is to actually use the key.
现在创建了一个"keeper".
It has created a keeper.
我们可以检查这两个文件现在是否在".ssh"下,
We can check that these two files are now under ".ssh".
我们可以看到...
And we can see...
我们有这两个文件:
We have these two files:
我们有25519和公钥.
we have the 25519 and the public key.
如果我们通过 "cat" 命令查看这个密钥,那么这个密钥实际上不是什么复杂的二进制文件,
And if we "cat" through the output, that key is actually not like any fancy binary file,
它只是一个文本文件,里面包含了公钥和一些别名,
it's just a text file that has the contents of the public key and some alias name for it,
这样我们就知道这个公钥是什么.
so we can know what this public key is.
我们告诉服务器
The way we can tell the server that
我们有 ssh 授权,
we're authorized to ssh there is by just actually copying this file,
可以通过将这个文件复制到 ".ssh/authorized_keys" 文件中来
like copying this string into a file, that is ".ssh/authorized_keys".
这里
So here what I'm doing is
我正在使用 "cat" 命令来查看这个文件的输出,它只是一个我们想要复制的文本行,
I'm catting the output of this file which is just this line of text that we want to copy
然后将其传输到 ssh 中,
and I'm piping that into ssh
然后远程使用 "tee" 命令将标准输入的内容输入到 ".ssh/authorized_keys" 中.
and then remotely I'm asking "tee" to dump the contents of the standard input into ".ssh/authorized_keys".
如果我们这样做,显然会要求我们输入密码.
And if we do that, obviously it's gonna ask us for a password.
复制成功后,我们可以检查一下,如果再次尝试 ssh,
It was copied, and now we can check that if we try to ssh again,
它会首先要求我们输入密码,但是你可以安排在会话中保存密码,
It's gonna first ask us for a passphrase but you can arrange that so that it's saved in the session
这样我们就不必为服务器输入密钥.
and we didn't actually have to type the key for the server.
我可以再次演示一下.
And I can kind of show that again.
还有更多有用的内容.
More things that are useful.
哦,我们可以做...
Oh, we can do...
如果那个命令看起来有点奇怪,
If that command seemed a little bit janky,
你实际上可以使用专门为此构建的命令,
you can actually use this command that is built for this,
这样你就不必构建那个很长的命令了.
so you don't have to kind of craft this "ssh" command.
这个命令就叫做 "ssh-copy-id".
That is just called "ssh-copy-id".
我们可以做同样的事情,它会复制密钥.
And we can do the same and it's gonna copy the key.
现在,如果我们尝试 ssh,
And now, if we try to ssh,
我们可以在不输入任何密钥或密码的情况下进行 ssh.
we can ssh without actually typing any key at all, or any password.
还有一件事儿.
More things.
我们可能想要复制文件.
We will probably want to copy files.
你不能使用 "cp" 命令,但可以使用 "scp" 命令,即 "ssh 复制".
You cannot use "cp" but you can use "scp", for "ssh copy".
在这里,我们可以指定要复制的本地文件名为 "notes.md",语法和"mv"有些相似.
And here we can specify that we want to copy this local file called notes and the syntax is kind of similar.
我们要将它复制到远程这个位置,然后使用";"分隔要复制到的路径.
We want to copy to this remote and then we have a semicolon to separate what the path is going to be.
然后我们指定要将其复制为 "notes",但我们也可以将其复制为 "foobar".
And then we have oh, we want to copy this as "notes" but we could also copy this as "foobar".
如果我们这样做,它将被执行,并告诉我们所有的内容都已经被复制到那里了.
And if we do that, it has been executed and it's telling us that all the contents have been copied there.
如果你要复制很多文件,那么你应该使用一个更好的命令,
If you're gonna be copying a lot of files, there is a better command that you should be using
它叫做 "rsync".例如,在这里仅通过指定这三个标志,
that is called "rsync". For example, here just by specifying these three flags,
我告诉 "rsync" 在可能的情况下保留所有权限,
I'm telling "rsync" bo kind of preserve all the permissions whenever possible
以尝试检查文件是否已经被复制.
to try to check if the file has already been copied.
例如,"scp"将尝试复制已经存在的文件.
For example, "scp" will try to copy files that are already there.
例如,如果你在复制过程中断开连接,
This will happen for example if you are trying to copy and the connection interrupts in the middle of it.
"scp"会从头开始复制每个文件,
"scp" will start from the very beginning, trying to copy every file,
而"rsync"会从停止的地方继续.
whereas "rsync" will continue from where it stopped.
在这里,我们要求它复制整个文件夹,
And here, we ask it to copy the entire folder
它只需要很快地复制整个文件夹.
and it's just really quickly copied the entire folder.
关于ssh的另一个需要知道的事情是,
One of the other things to know about ssh is that
".ssh/config"是ssh的dotfiles的等效文件.
the equivalent of the dotfile for ssh is the ".ssh/config".
因此,如果我们编辑ssh配置文件,
So if we edit the ".ssh/config" to be..
如果我将ssh配置文件编辑成这样,就不必每次都输入
If I edit the ssh config to look something like this, instead of having to, every time, type "ssh jjgo",
"ssh jjgo"这个非常长的字符串,这样我就可以引用特定的远程主机.
like having this really long string so I can like refer to this specific remote, I want to refer, with the specific user name,
我想引用特定的用户名,我可以在这里加上一些内容,例如这是用户名,这是主机名,
I can have something here like that says this is the username, this is the host name,
该主机所指的内容以及你应该使用这个身份验证文件.
that this host is referring to and you should use this identity file.
如果我将此内容复制到本地文件夹中,
And if I copy this,this is right now in my local folder,
我可以将其复制到ssh中.
I can copy this into ssh.
现在,不用输入这个很长的命令
Now, instead of having to do this really long command,
我只需要说我想要ssh连接到名为VM的主机.
I can just say I just want to ssh into the host called VM.
通过这样做,它会从ssh配置中获取所有的配置并将其应用于这里.
And by doing that, it's grabbing all that configuration from the ".ssh/config" and applying it here.
这个解决方案比创建ssh别名之类的东西要好得多,
And this solution is much better than something like creating an alias for ssh,
因为像"scp"和"rsync"这样的其他程序也知道ssh的dotfiles,
because other programs like "scp" and "rsync" also know about the dotfiles for ssh
并且在有时会使用它们.
and will use them whenever they are there.
关于远程机器,我最后要介绍的是在这里,
Last thing I want to cover about remote machines is that here,
例如,我们将有tmux,
for example, we'll have tmux and we can, like I was saying before,
我们可以像之前说的那样开始编辑某个文件并开始运行某个作业.
we can start editing some file and we can start running some job.
例如,像"htop"这样的东西.
For example, something like "htop".
这正在运行,我们可以从中分离,关闭连接,然后再次ssh.
And this is running here, we can detach from it, close the connection and then ssh back.
然后,如果你执行`tmux a`,一切都与你离开的状态一样,
And then, if you do "tmux a", everything is as you left it,
就好像什么也没有改变.
like nothing has really changed.
如果在后台有执行的事情,它们将继续执行.
And like if you have things executing there in the background, they will keep executing.
我想这就是我要讲的有关这个工具的所有内容.
I think that, pretty much, ends all I have to say for this tool.
关于远程机器有什么问题吗?
Any questions related to remote machines?
这是一个非常好的问题.让我想想该怎么回答.
That's a really good question. So what I do for that,
哦,是的,抱歉.问题是,如何在本地机器上使用tmux,
Oh, yes, sorry. So the question is, how do you deal with trying to use tmux in your local machine,
同时又要在远程机器上使用tmux?
and also trying to use tmux in the remote machine?
有几个处理这个问题的技巧.
There are a couple of tricks for dealing with that.
第一个是更改前缀.
The first one is changing the prefix.
例如,我在本地机器上将前缀从"Ctrl+B"更改为"Ctrl+A",
So what I do, for example, is in my local machine the prefix I have changed from "Ctrl+B" to "Ctrl+A" and
然后在远程机器上仍为"Ctrl+B".
then in remove machines this is still "Ctrl+B".
所以我可以在两者之间切换,
So I can kind of swap between,
如果我想对本地的tmux执行操作,
if I want to do things to the local tmux
我会按"Ctrl+A",如果我想对远程的tmux执行操作,我会按"Ctrl+B".
I will do "Ctrl+A" and if I want to do things to the remote tmux I would do "Ctrl+B".
另一件事是你可以有不同的配置文件,
Another thing is that you can have separate configs,
所以我可以做类似于这样的事情......
so I can do something like this, and then...
哦,因为我没有自己的ssh配置文件.
Ah, because I don't have my own ssh config, yeah.
但如果你......
But if you...
嗯,我可以`ssh VM`.
Um, I can `ssh VM`.
这里,你看到的两个条之间的差异,
Here, what you see, the difference between these two bars,
例如,是因为tmux配置不同.
for example, is because the tmux config is different.
就像你将在练习中看到的那样,tmux配置在".tmux.conf"文件中,
As you will see in the exercises, the tmux configuration is in the ".tmux.conf"
你可以在".tmux.conf"中做很多事情,
And in ".tmux.conf", here you can do a lot of things
比如根据你所在的主机更改颜色,
like changing the color depending on the host you are...
以便快速获得视觉反馈,
so you can get like quick visual feedback about where you are,
或者如果你有一个嵌套会话.
or like if you have a nested session.
此外,
Also, tmux will...
如果你在同一台主机上,并且尝试在一个tmux会话中使用tmux,
if you're in the same host and you try to tmux within a tmux session,
tmux会阻止你这样做,以避免出现问题.
it will kind of prevent you from doing it so you don't run into issues.
如果有关我们涵盖的所有主题的其他问题,请随意问.
Any other questions related, to kind of all the topics we have covered.
对于那个问题的另一个答案是,
Another answer to that question is also,
如果你将前缀键击两次,它会将其发送一次到底层shell.
if you type the prefix twice, it sends it once to the underlying shell.
因此,本地绑定是"Ctrl+A",远程绑定是"Ctrl+A",
So the local binding is "Ctrl+A" and the remote binding is "Ctrl+A",
你可以键入"Ctrl+A","Ctrl+A",然后键入"D",例如从远程分离.
You could type "Ctrl+A", "Ctrl+A" and then "D", for example, detaches from the remote, basically.
我想今天的课程到此结束了,
I think that ends the class for today,
有很多与所有这些主题相关的练习,
there's a bunch of exercises related to all these main topics
我们今天也有办公时间.
and we're gonna be holding office hours today, too.
可以随时来问我们任何问题.
So feel free to come and ask us any questions.